SHANTEL A. MARTINEZ

[w] shantel-martinez.github.io [e] shantel.a.martinez@gmail.com

Career focus is on contributing novel genetic research within agriculture using advanced statistical methods while maintaining direct application towards helping farmers. Believes strongly in being able to **communicate** science to non-scientists, **mentoring** young scientists and peers, along with cultivating a **collaborative work environment** as career priorities.

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Molecular Plant Science, Washington State University, Pullman WA 2018 M.S., Crop Science, Washington State University, Pullman WA 2013 B.S., Bioengineering, Washington State University, Pullman WA 2011

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Wheat Molecular Genetics and Prediction Modeling

Post-doctoral | Dr. Mark E. Sorrells Lab 2018 - Mar 2020

TOPIC: Producing genomic prediction models on large-scale wheat genomic and phenotypic datasets to reduce grain sprouting when certain climate patterns, such as heavy rainfall during harvest time, increase. SKILLS: Quantitative genetics, strong daily R use, git version control, genomic prediction using ridge and Bayesian regression models, strong layman communication, basic python and bash, electronic lab notebook techniques

Improving Germplasm Resources for the Northwest

PhD | Dr. Camille M. Steber and Dr. Kimberly Garland Campbell Labs 2013 - 2018

TOPIC: After the 2016 Low Falling Numbers crisis, wheat farmers needed an immediate solution to ensure their crop would not succumb to the loss of millions of dollars they had just experienced. My research on preharvest sprouting tolerance (PHS) and Falling Numbers was accelerated to meet these demands. After screening 469 PNW wheat breeding lines, I identified 12 new genetic locations that WSU and USDA wheat breeders immediately used to introgress tolerance into their germplasm. Increased grower knowledge on agronomic best practices were also a result of this project.

SKILLS: Comprehensive markdown use, **large-scale field data collection and coordination**, technical writing, applied plant breeding, **quality R data visualization** and slide design, mutation genetics

Investigating a PHS Tolerant Wheat Mutant

MS | Dr. Camille M. Steber and Dr. Arron H. Carter Labs 2011 - 2013

TOPIC: Worked with a molecular geneticist and a wheat breeder to find an applied solution to PHS susceptibility through mutation genetics and field trials. This basic/applied hybrid research experience resulted in learning how to balance an attention-to-detail molecular approach while keeping the large-scale agronomic breeding scope in mind.

SKILLS: SAS, **research-based statistics**, hormone seed biology, lab notebook techniques, **cereal crop field practices**

COMMUNICATION

INVITED TALKS | TECHNICAL

- Soft Wheat Quality Council Meeting, Raleigh, NC. Identifying Loci and Genomic Prediction Models for PHS
 Tolerance in Northeast Soft Wheat Breeding Programs 2019
- 2. <u>Western Wheat Quality Meeting: Falling Numbers Workshop</u>, Portland, OR. The First Step to Tackling the FN Problem: Identifying Tolerant Genes/QTL in PNW Germplasm 2019
- 3. <u>International Seed Science Society Conference</u>, Monterey, CA. Identification of a Locus Corresponding to the Preharvest Sprouting Tolerance Mutant, ERA8, in Wheat 2017
- 4. <u>ASA, CSSA, SSSA International Annual Meeting</u>, Phoenix, AZ. Genome-wide Association Mapping of Preharvest Sprouting in PNW White Winter Wheat 2016
- 5. <u>Plant and Animal Genome Conference</u>, San Diego, CA. Higher Seed Dormancy and ABA Sensitivity Improves Wheat Preharvest Sprouting Tolerance 2016

OUTREACH | NON-TECHNICAL

- 1. Small Grains Field Days | Audience: Farmers, Breeders, Pathologists
- 2. Grow NYC Variety Showcase | Audience: Chefs, Public, Fresh Market Buyers
- 3. MPS Plant Science Day | Audience: Parents and Children K-8
- 4. WSU Extension Wheat Academy Workshop | Audience: **Producers**, Farmers, Commissioners
- 5. LSAMP End of the Year Banquet Keynote Speaker | Audience: Undergraduates in STEM
- 6. Future Cougars of Color Plant Science Workshop | Audience: High School Students

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Large-Scale Field Experiments: Washington cereal breeders and colleagues often requested my field **management skills** for projects that require succinct coordination of large labor teams (20+ people) while maintaining timely execution of the experiment (i.e. before the heat becomes a danger).

SciComm Workshop: three-day training on **communicating science** to the laymen audiences 2019

Journal Peer Reviewer: Agronomy, Molecular Breeding, Theoretical and Applied Genetics

Director of Professional Development 2016-2017

During my PhD, a handful of graduate students and I noticed a need for opportunities to develop professional skills across all disciplines that just weren't being met within graduate programs. With this crucial need in mind, the Professional Development Initiative (PDI) was created and in one year we implemented 30 new professional development events, served over 1,800 attendees, coordinated and lead 11 graduate student senators, and sat on both the PDI and GPSA Executive Board.

SKILLS: **Efficient peer-to-peer communication**, **interdisciplinary collaboration**, conflict resolution, leadership, professionalism, **strong organization**, built relationships with top-level university leadership

MENTORING | SELECTED

Katherine Roberts, Project Awards: 1st Place Plant Science, New York HS Science Program 2018 Samantha Beck, Project Awards: 1st Place Molecular Biology, CAHNRS Internship Program 2017

DEPARTMENTAL SERVICES | SELECTED

- Corteva Plant Breeding Symposium Committee Role: Host speakers, implementation of symposium 2019
- WSU Upward Bound Internship Program Role: Recruiter, volunteer, mentor
 2009-2015

TECHNICAL PUBLICATIONS

- 1. **Martinez, S.A.**, Godoy J., Huang M., Zhang Z., Carter A.H., Garland Campbell, K.A., and Steber, C.M. (2018a). Genome-Wide Association Mapping for Tolerance to Preharvest Sprouting and Low Falling Numbers in Wheat. <u>Frontiers in Plant Science</u>. 9, 1-16.
- 2. **Martinez, S.A.**, Thompson A.L., Wen N., Murphy L., Sanquinet K.A., M., Steber, C.M., and Garland Campbell, K. (2018b). Registration of the Louise/Alpowa Wheat Recombinant Inbred Line Mapping Population. <u>Journal of Plant Registrations</u>.
- 3. **Martinez, S.A.**, Tuttle, K., Takebayashi, Y., Seo, M., Garland Campbell, K., and Steber, C.M. (2016). The Wheat ABA Hypersensitive ERA8 Mutant is Associated with Increased Preharvest Sprouting Tolerance and Altered Hormone Accumulation. <u>Euphytica</u>. 212, 229-245.
- 4. Tuttle, K.M., **Martinez, S.A.**, Schramm, E.C., Takebayashi, Y., Seo, M., and Steber, C.M. (2015). Grain dormancy loss is associated with changes in ABA and GA sensitivity and hormone accumulation in bread wheat, Triticum aestivum (L.). <u>Seed Science Research</u> 1–15.
- 5. **Martinez, S.A.**, Schramm, E.C., Harris, T.J., Kidwell, K.K., Garland-Campbell, K., and Steber, C.M. (2014). Registration of Zak Soft White Spring Wheat Germplasm with Enhanced Response to ABA and Increased Seed Dormancy. <u>Journal of Plant Registrations</u> 8, 217-220.

REFERENCES

Dr. Mark E. Sorrells

Professor of Plant Breeding and Genetics Plant Breeding and Genetics Section Cornell University

Phone: 1-607-255-1665 mes12@cornell.edu

Dr. Camille M. Steber

Molecular Geneticist

USDA - Agricultural Research Services

Wheat Health, Genetics, and Quality Research Unit

Phone: 1-509-335-2887 csteber@wsu.edu

Dr. Kimberly A. Garland Campbell

Research Geneticist

USDA - Agricultural Research Services

Wheat Health, Genetics, and Quality Research Unit

Phone: 1-509-335-0582 kgcamp@wsu.edu

Dr. Arron H. Carter

Associate Professor and O.A. Vogel Endowed Chair of Wheat Breeding and Genetics Department of Crop and Soil Sciences

Washington State University

Phone: 1-509-335-6198 ahcarter@wsu.edu